American Vaudeville Museum collection, 1850s-2007 (bulk 1910s-1940s)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
- Series XXI: Leon Errol Collection, 1904-1940s, 1.25 linear feet
  Leon Errol (1876 or 1881?-1951) was born in Australia, and began performing in college, circus, Shakespeare and light operas while still there. He migrated to the U.S. by 1904 with his dance partner, Stella Chatelaine (1886-1946). He performed cockney songs and eccentric dance in variety saloons and partnered with Pete Gerald as "Gerald and Errol", featuring German ("Dutch") or Irish dialect comedy, ragtime piano, burlesque boxing, and a trained bulldog named Buck. They played alongside Gale Dauvrey and Alf T. Lane in "A Wife's Folly", an Edward Shields Company comedy drama, ca. 1904, in Baker City, Oregon. The trio of Gerald, Errol and Dauvrey performed in Walla Walla, Washington in 1904. Errol was stage manager for the Orpheum Theatre in Portland, Oregon during the 1904-05 season. He also performed in their productions, directing a group known as "Errol's Burlesquers" which includes future Keystone comedian Roscoe Arbuckle. Errol performed in numerous productions at LaVern's Park in Walla Walla, and at Shields' Park in Portland during this time. He and Will Gross, as "Errol and Gross", performed ragtime musicals. In 1906 Errol was traveling with Zinn's Travesty Company, which performed in San Francisco in 1906 and was there when the earthquake hit.
  Leon Errol and Stella Chatelaine married in 1906. By 1911 they had arrived in New York with their burlesque comedy show, The Lilies or The Jersey Lillies. At Abe Erlanger’s (Ziegfeld’s financial backer) insistence, Leon was soon engaged by Florenz Ziegfeld in his Broadway debut, "The Winsome Widow", and then in the Ziegfeld Follies (1911-1915), in which Stella Chatelaine also performed. He co-produced and performed in two shows of "Hitchy Koo", the second in 1918. Errol was known for his dialect roles, which he originally developed to camouflage his strong Australian accent, as an eccentric dancer-physical comedian and for his comic gait as a "stage inebriate" or other eccentric role. He is especially remembered for his long-running series of short comic films for RKO Radio Pictures, beginning in 1934 and continuing until his death in 1951.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1904-1906, Note: fragile; see reference photocopy in Box 60 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1910-1918, Note: fragile; see reference photocopy in Box 60 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Papers, miscellaneous (Box 60, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, ca. 1925-1940s (Box 60, Folder 2)
  - Film Fan Monthly, no. 109-110 ( July-Aug. 1970) (Box 60, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook 1, 1904-1906 (reference photocopy) (Box 60, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1910-1918 (reference photocopy) (Box 60, Folder 5)
- Series XXII: Belle Story Collection, ca. 1914-1920, 1 linear foot
  Provenance
  This scrapbook was given by Belle Story to Eulalio Estrella, who had lived with her in Winnetka, Illinois from 1968 to 1970, when she sold her house there. He took the scrapbook to Brazil. Three decades later his stepson's fiancée found it there and brought it back to the United States with Estrella's permission; it was donated by her to the American Vaudeville Museum collection around 2000.
  This series comprises a scrapbook of newspaper clippings, theater programs and other printed matter, and one photograph, 1914-1920, documenting the career of the soprano singer Belle Story (sometimes spelled Storey). There is also correspondence with biographical information from Belle Story's daughter, and programs (two in photocopy form) provided by her of Belle Story's performances at the Hotel Biltmore and Carnegie Hall.
  Belle Story (née Grace Leard, born 1887) was the daughter of a Midwestern Presbyterian minister who encouraged her musical training but not her stage career. She studied voice with Mme. Marcella Sembrich, and traveled to Europe around 1906 with a group to study music. She took her stage name from the maiden name of her mother, which was Storey, but she later shortened it.
  By 1916 she had toured as a vaudeville singer for several years and performed at theaters including the Hippodrome in New York and the Temple in Boston and Detroit. Songs she was known for at the time included "Chin-Chin Open Your Heart", from Montgomery & Stone's "Chin-Chin, Or A Modern Aladdin" (1914); and "The Flower Garden Ball." She also performed in "Hip Hip Hooray" at the Hippodrome beginning in June 1916. She was featured in a cover article of B.F. Keith's Theatre News in May 1916. That year, at age twenty-eight, she married a Wall Street broker from Chicago, Frederic E. Andrews.
  In 1917 she focused on a concert career, performing with pianist Leopold Godowsky in a program with the Russian Symphony Orchestra at Carnegie Hall, and with Enrico Caruso at the Biltmore Musicales. A promotional booklet from that time called her "America's greatest coloratura singer." Her voice was described as sweet, flute-like, and bird-like. According to her daughter, Belle was the first person to sing "Over There" in public, at a Liberty Bond rally, before it was officially published in 1917. In 1918 she performed again at the Hippodrome, as several different characters including "Columbia" in a fifteen-act musical spectacle, "Everything" by R H. Burnside.
  Aside from her participation in a benefit concert in 1920, there is no later information provided in the scrapbook about Belle Story's career. (An undated loose clipping with no evident relationship to her describes a May Day children's festival in Los Angeles, and mentions a young Martha Graham as mistress of ceremonies.) She retired completely from performance upon remarrying four years after the death of her first husband (ca. 1930), and moved to Texas.
  Related Material
  The Hippodrome souvenir book for 1918, which includes the program for "Everything" in which Belle Story performed several roles, is in the Theatres series, subseries 3: Souvenir Programs, Box 20.
  - Note re: scrapbook provenance from Alicia Shirakbari, ca. 2000, Correspondence between Frank Cullen and Mrs. Walter Watson, July 2000 (Box 61, Folder 1)
  - Programs, from Mrs. Walter Watson (Box 61, Folder 2)
  - Printed matter, separated from scrapbook (Box 61, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1914-1920 - reference photocopy (Box 61, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, ca. 1914-1920, Note: fragile, not available for viewing (Box 61, Folder 5)
- Series XXIII: McWatters-Tyson Collection, ca. 1898-1936, bulk 1910s-ca. 1925, .25 linear foot
  This series consists of photographs, printed matter, a newspaper clipping, photocopies, and correspondence documenting the career of Arthur J. McWatters and Grace Tyson. Arthur's surname is sometimes spelled McWaters. There is a color copy of a 1902 document from Herrman the magician, giving McWatters exclusive permission to perform one of his own illusions. A 1903 Saginaw program lists McWatters & Tyson Co. performing "Scenes in a Dressing Room." Most of the photographs are of McWatters and Tyson, but also include other performers. Some of these toured as part of McWatters & Tyson & Co. There are also photographs of Bessie Burton (of Tyler & Burton), Hal David, and Fred Nolan. One color snapshot depicts a poster of McWatters & Tyson in company with John and Ethel Barrymore. A copy of a family photograph from 1936 is included. The correspondence is from Evan S. Williams, the son of McWatters' niece Helen Southgate Williams; he donated the collection to the American Vaudeville Museum in 2004.
  Arthur McWatters (1871-1963) grew up in Saginaw, Michigan, and returned there throughout his life to hunt and fish in the area. He taught piano and organ there as a young man, and advertised himself as a "tenor balladist" already with several compositions to his name. In the mid-1890s he and three friends went to New York to seek careers there. By around 1900 he and Grace Tyson (d.1942), who became his wife, were appearing together as McWatters & Tyson. They sang, danced, and did comic skits, with Arthur playing guitar and banjo as well as piano. In 1913-14 they toured to South Africa and London. At that time Grace was touted as "the actress whose eyes are insured for £5000." They continued performing in an active tour schedule until at least the mid-1920s. With Grace's death in 1942 at around age sixty, Arthur retired from the stage and managed a chain of movie theaters around Freeport, Long Island, where they had been living. He died at age ninety-two.
  - Correspondence (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Papers (Box 61, Folder 7)
  - Photographs (Box 61, Folder 8)
- Series XXIV: Willie, West & McGinty Collection, ca. 1930s, 1 linear foot
  This series comprises photographs, photocopies and other papers, and props related to the career of Willie, West and McGinty, a comedy team sometimes described as “The Comedy Builders.” The props consist of a carpenter’s apron and two large corncob-style pipes. The photocopies include a step-by-step record, attributed to Ted Corradine, of the Willie West and McGinty stage routine and a playbill for Judy Garland and her International Variety Show that includes Willie, West and McGinty, “A Billion Building Blunders.” A poster from this collection is stored separately with the Posters and Oversize Items series, Box 23..
  These materials were [apparently] donated to the American Vaudeville Museum by Bill West's granddaughter, Robin Doolan Geoffrion.
  Bill Briscoe (1886-1949) began his career as a comic acrobat in a team known as Wild and West, which toured internationally. He and Frank Crossley (ca. 1882-ca. 1942), both from Lancashire, England, developed a carpenter slapstick act as Willie West & McGinty (no comma) around 1900, while en route to perform a gymnast act in Australia, discarding that form in favor of acrobatic comedy. Willie West was played by Briscoe, who later went by the name William, Willie, Bill, or Billy West, Sr.
  A third unidentified member joined the original two in the role of Mr. Willie while they were still in Lancashire, and the comma was added to the act's name from that time on, though irregularly. This third role was played by Rue Corré from around 1923, prior to their immigration to the U.S.; he also was from Lancashire.
  The trio moved to the U.S. under the auspices of Florenz Ziegfeld for the Follies of 1923. They performed a skillfully choreographed clumsy carpenter act in worn work clothing, with props including tools, boards, pails, and a ladder. Their routine emphasized physical slapstick rather than verbal exchange. The group continued to be successful through the Depression, touring in London and elsewhere in Europe in the late 1930s, as well as in Australia and South Africa. They appeared in several films (both short and feature-length) in the 1930s, beginning with "Plastered" in 1930.
  Willie, West & McGinty carried on with second-generation members into the 1950s, and appeared on television, including The Colgate Comedy Hour in 1951. Billy West, Jr. (1909-1971) joined the act in 1929 at age 19, and replaced his father in later years. Frank Crossley's son, Frank Crossley, Jr. (ca. 1910 - ca. 1997) replaced his father as Ted McGinty. Ted Corradine (ca. 1896-1975), also from Lancashire, became McGinty in the early 1940s. Donald Keith was playing the third role by 1958.
  - Papers, miscellaneous (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Photocopies (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - Photographs (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Work apron (Box 62)
  - Tobacco pipes (2) (Box 62)
  - Poster - "Willie, West & McGinty", 1940s (George A. Hamid and Son), (stored in Box 23, Posters and Oversize Items)
- Series XXV: Paul Gerard Smith Collection, ca.1918-1960, ca. 2000-2001, 1.25 linear feet
  Paul Gerard Smith's materials include correspondence between his grandson, Paul Gerard Smith III, and Frank Cullen (American Vaudeville Museum), and drafts of his biography by Paul Gerard Smith III and Frank Cullen. Also included are a chronology, "Adventures in Show Business"; performer and sketch indexes; and a list of credits compiled by Paul Gerard Smith. There are photocopies of typewritten scripts with handwritten notations from the early 1920s and 1930s.. An album of clippings includes his pre-vaudeville years, beginning in 1918 when he enlisted in the Marines, and mentions his service in Germany where he produced the Sixth Marine Revue for fellow "doughboys" in 1919. Most of the clippings are from the 1920s and 1930s, with the source not generally given; some playbills are included.
  Paul Gerard Smith was born in Omaha, Nebraska on September 14, 1894 and died April 4, 1968 in San Diego, California. He also lived in Chicago, where he met and married Mary Alice Lundgren in 1919. Sometime after 1919 he moved to New York City where he began writing for vaudeville acts, including the Ziegfeld Follies (1924-1925). From 1920 to 1927 Paul Gerard Smith, Inc. also produced and booked over 100 vaudeville acts. He moved to California around 1927, at the request of Buster Keaton, to work on adapting the film "The General." Over the years he wrote or contributed to over 90 film scripts. Most of his work was as a "script doctor" - he would fix scripts and not necessarily receive credit for his work. He served in the Marines during World War I and in the USO during World War II, and wrote various scripts for plays and revues in the postwar years.
  - Correspondence between Paul Gerard Smith III and Frank Cullen, 2000-2001 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - "Adventures in Show Business" - chronology, 1918- ca. 1950s (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Biographical drafts (Box 63, Folder 3)
    Drafts by Paul Gerard Smith III, ca. 2000 (2 versions)
    Draft by Paul Gerard Smith III and Frank Cullen, ca. 2000
  - Indexes (Box 63, Folder 4)
    Vaudeville Performer Index
    Vaudeville Sketch Index
    Vaudeville Acts/Sketches Produced But Not in Files
  - Papers, miscellaneous (Box 63, Folder 5)
    Friars Club program in form of menu, "Paul & Joe's Table d'hote Frolic", cooked up by Friar Joe Laurie, Jr., and Friar Paul Gerard Smith, Nov. 28th, 1926
    Full-page ad by Paul Gerard Smith, Variety, 1921 (in 2 pieces)
    Photocopies:
    Full-page ads (2) by Paul Gerard Smith, Variety, 1921
    "Your Broadway and Mine" column by Walter Winchell, text contributed by Paul Gerard Smith, New York Evening Graphic, July 15, 1927
    "Odyssey of a literary vagabond" by David Arlen, Script (?), ca. 1936-37, pp. 39-42 (photocopy)
    "A thumbnose sketch - Paul G. Smith" by Joe Laurie, Jr., unidentified newspaper, Nov. 26, 1947
    "Famed author recalls years with Broadway greats for Hemet group" by Bea Gaines, The Hemet News (Calif.), ca. 1960
  - Photographs of Paul Gerard Smith, ca. 1920s-1930s (digital copies and photocopies) (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - Stage and Pictures Credits, 1923-1940s (2 versions, compiled 1946-ca. 1947) (Box 63, Folder 7)
  - Typescripts (Box 63, Folder 8)
    "Comedy Writer", undated (poem)
    "The Unknown Sucker", undated (poem)
    "The Suspense Is Terrible", ca. 1922
    "Beautiful - But Dumb": A Skit for Eight Women, 1923
    "Beautiful But Dumb" (New Version), ca. 1923
    "Clark & McCullough in Le Grande Cafe", ca. 1936
    "The Yellow Peril", 1926
    "Curtain Call", ca. 1938
    Untitled, ca. 1950-1951
    "Hero", undated (film script)
  - Clippings (reference photocopies) (Box 63, Folder 9)
  - Clippings album, ca. 1918-1932 (rehoused ca. 2000) (Box 64)
- Series XXVI: Fan Scrapbook Collection, ca. 1897-1914, ca. 1930-1935, 2 linear feet
  This collection comprises four scrapbooks created by unidentified, unrelated collectors, of magazine and newspaper clippings of actresses and actors as well as playbills and program clippings, around the first decade of the twentieth century.
  Fan scrapbook 1 (1911-1912) comprises primarily clipped reviews of silent films from Bison, Edison, Itala, Kalem, Lux, Nestor, Pathe, Powers, Selig, Solax, Thanhouser, Yankee, and other film companies. There is a program for a chamber concert at Faneuil Hall. There are some tipped-in reproduced portraits, as well as an ad for portraits of "Photo-Player Favorites" from Kalem Company, and one for "Some Notable Vitagraph Players." There is also a handwritten shopping list, and a handwritten summary of theatre programs from January to April 1912, including cast notes. It was apparently assembled by a Boston area resident.
  Fan scrapbook 2 (ca. 1897-1935, bulk ca. 1900-1907) consists primarily of magazine clippings of stage stars, usually depicted in roles. The subjects include Ethel Barrymore, Mrs. Patrick Campbell, Lulu Glaser, Ellen Goodrich, Ada Rehan, Blanche Ring, Valeska Suratt ("The Original Gibson Girl"), Ellen Terry, and Edith and Mabel Taliaferro. Some group stage portraits are included. There are a few added loose magazine and newspaper clippings from the 1930s.
  Fan scrapbook 3 (ca. 1909-1911) is a hand-bound, uniformly presented set of "Photographic Art Studies of Stage Favorites." They are reproductions on glossy paper of photographic portraits, each with an ornate decorative line surround. The portraits range from bust to full-length, generally with elegant dress. There are some posed group stage scenes. Several of the subjects are identified as being in vaudeville. The photographers are White, Sarony, Otto Sarony Co., Frank C. Bangs, and Hall (all of New York); and Jens R. Matzene, Melvin H. Sykes, and Moffett Studio (all of Chicago). There are title pages from several issues of Smith's Magazine, ranging from May 1909 to January 1911, which apparently was the source of all the pages included in this scrapbook. The issues indicated are:
  v.9 no.1 (Apr 1909), no.2 (May 1909)
  v.10 no.5 (Feb 1910)
  v.11 no.3 (Jun 1910)
  v.12 no.1 (Oct 1910), no.4 (Jan 1911)
  Fan scrapbook 4 (ca. 1905-1914) consists of clippings from magazines and newspapers (predominantly portraits rather than text), as well as playbills and program clippings. There are some loose clippings and playbills from 1907-1914. Performers documented in this scrapbook include aerialists such as Charmion, the Sisters Macarte, and the Four Harveys; and stage actors Dan Crimmons and Rosa Gore, George H. Primrose, O'Brien and Havel, Belle Blanche, May Ward, Catherine Countiss, Eva Tanguay, Emma Francis, Eugenie Fougere, Una Clayton, Louise Le Baron, and Jane Oaker. Some performances recorded here are "The Hurdy Gurdy Girl" (1907) featuring Mae Botti, "The Earl and the Girl", "Wine, Woman and Song" featuring Bonita, "The Man of the Hour" with Lillian Kemble, the Clyde Fitch comedy "Girls" ( 1908 ), and Christie MacDonald in "Miss Hook of Holland" (1908) and several other plays.
  This scrapbook is housed in a ledger book on detached pages. Some of the pages are lined, from a separate late-nineteenth-century accounting ledger; their contents are from the first decade of the twentieth century. Although most are numbered in pencil (apparently at a later stage), the original page order is not evident. There are some loose clippings and playbills from ca. 1907-1914 as well, which include portraits of Fanny Stedman, Vera Curtis, Bertie Herron, and Burdella Patterson. There is some indication that the collector lived in Boston and Maine.. The scrapbook was donated to the American Vaudeville Museum by Linda Richards, a Maine resident.
  - Fan scrapbook 1, 1911-1912 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - Fan scrapbook 2, ca. 1897-1935 (bulk ca. 1900-1907) (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Fan scrapbook 3, ca. 1909-1911 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - Fan scrapbook 4, ca. 1905-1914 (Box 66)
- Series XXVII: Films, ca. 1930-1947, 2.75 linear feet
  This series consists of 16mm films in a variety of lengths. The films with original packaging mostly intact are from Official Films, Inc. The known dates range from ca.1930-1947; one, Charlie Chaplin's Hits of the Past, was originally released in 1914 as The Property Man. The longest of them, Merry-Go-Round of 1938, is notable for the inclusion of two vaudeville/revue routines: "Song of the Woodsman" performed by Bert Lahr, and "River Stay 'Way from My Door" performed by Jimmy Savo.
  - 3-1/2 inch reel (Box 67)
    Concert Canteen - Rubinoff (1945; Music Hall Varieties, from Official Films, Inc., Ridgefield, N.J.; production no. 20604)
  - 7 inch reels
    Charlie Chaplin, Hits of the Past (An Official Films movie; title on film lead)
    News Review of 1947 (Official Films Inc., News Thrills; title on box)
    A Present for Santa Claus (title on film lead; lacks container)
    The Rag Dog, 1935 (Official Films Inc., Merry-Toons Cartoons; title on box)
    Unidentified - Long - Frees on the R... (written on film tail; An Official Films movie)
  - 7 inch reels (Box 68)
    Bismarck Sea Victory, ca. 1942 (title on container)
    Flowers (title on container)
    Jungle Jinks, 1930 (title on film lead)
    Lindbergh (title on container)
    Roosevelt, or T.R. Himself (title on film lead)
  - 13-3/4 inch reels (Box 69)
    Merry-Go-Round of 1938 (2 reels)
- Series XXVIII: Media, ca. 2000-2007, .75 linear foot
  This series includes audio cassettes, compact disks, zip drives, and 3-1/4 inch disks; contents include images, text, and sound. Some are commercially produced works or copies thereof; some were created by donors of other materials to this collection; and some are files created by the American Vaudeville Museum. Printouts have been provided when feasible.
  - Audio cassettes (Box 70, Folder 1)
    Three X Sisters - Pearl Santos - Discography Project by Glenn Santos
    Clarice Vance, Sweet Singer of Southern Songs
  - Compact disks
    - Bindlestiff - Vaudeville Times photos - BFC [Bernard Frank Cullen] (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - Bobby May (images and text; 2nd disk is duplicate images) (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Capt. Anson Graphics (Rosenberg) (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Daniel Rosen Photos (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - Early Theatrical Posters, 1840-1936 (A2ZCDS, 2003; 2,124 images) (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - Family History, by Margaret Jeanne Ramirez (2001; text and images), (Includes biographies of Vaudeville performers Edward Santoro and Margaret Marlow, and their daughter "Baby" Victory Rose Santoro, who married Frank Ramirez; the latter were Margaret's parents) (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - Gildemeister, Vaudeville and Circus photos (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - The Great Tomsini & Co. (images) (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - Julian Eltinge Compilation Disk, from Mark Berger (images) (Box 70, Folder 10)
    - Larry Weeks (images) (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Levent, Vaudeville at Sea photos, disc #1 - Feb. 2004, (Levent & Mickey O'Connor live shots, plus ship photos - Sovereign of the Seas) - original in color (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - Levent's Last Di - last photos for VT [Vaudeville Times], (New Daniel Rosen headshots / Mickey O'Connor) - original in color (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - New York Clipper photos (1858, 1878, 1898 issues) (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Pandemonium! Hines, Hines and Dad (sound), (originally located with Thematic Subjects: Tap) (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Trixie Really Was a Friganza! (text [WordPerfect] and images) (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - Vaudeville at Sea - Alan Howard, Jay Johnson photos - some originals in color (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Vivace (sound/images) (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - 3-1/4 inch disks and zip drives
    - Balasi Family - Vaudeville Times Balasi history (disk) and images (zip drive), (Content of these disks is in the Balasi Family collection) (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - Bloolips poster (3 images of same poster on disk), (Original poster is in Posters and Oversize Items, Box 23) (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - BPL Saloon (zip drive with images - Adobe Photoshop files) (Box 71, Folder 10)
    - George Brown, speed walker (3 disks of images) (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - J.W. Kelly - Songster cover; J.W. Kelly stage persona; Maggie Cline, old age; M. Cline - Throw Him Down, McCloskey; Mike Kelly - Slide Kelly Slide (images) (Box 71, Folder 12)